I have a confession to make.
عندي اعتراف أخبركم به
As a scientist and engineer, I've focused on efficiency for many years.
كعالم ومهندس، ركزت على الفعالية لسنوات عديدة.
But efficiency can be a cult,
ولكن الفعالية يمكن أن تتحول لمعتقد،
and today I'd like to tell you about a journey
واليوم أود أن أحكي لكم عن رحلة
that moved me out of the cult and back to a far richer reality.
أخرجتني من هذا المعتقد وأعادتني إلى واقع أشد ثراءً.
A few years ago, after finishing my Ph.D. in London, I moved to Boston.
قبل بضع سنوات، وبعد حصولي على الدكتوراه في لندن، انتقلت إلى بوسطن.
I lived in Boston and worked in Cambridge.
عشت في بوسطن وعملت في جامعة كامبريدج.
I bought a racing bicycle that summer,
اشتريت دراجة سباق في ذلك الصيف،
and I bicycled every day to work.
وكنت استخدم الدراجة كل يوم للذهاب للعمل.
To find my way, I used my phone.
للبحث عن الطريق، استخدمت هاتفي.
It sent me over Mass. Ave., Massachusetts Avenue,
الذي أرشدني إلى شارع "ماساشوستس"،
the shortest route from Boston to Cambridge.
أقصر الطرق من بوسطن إلى كامبريدج.
But after a month
ولكن بعد شهر
that I was cycling every day on the car-packed Mass. Ave.,
من ركوبي للدراجة كل يوم ومروري بشارع "ماساشوستس"،
I took a different route one day.
أخذت طريقًا مختلفًا في أحد الأيام.
I'm not entirely sure why I took a different route that day, a detour.
ولم أكن متأكدًا تمامًا لماذا أخذت طريقًا مختلفًا في ذلك اليوم،
I just remember a feeling of surprise;
أتذكر فقط شعوري بالدهشة.
surprise at finding a street with no cars,
تفاجأت بالعثور على شارع خال من السيارات،
as opposed to the nearby Mass. Ave. full of cars;
عكس "ماساشوستس"، المكتظ بالسيارات؛
surprise at finding a street draped by leaves and surrounded by trees.
تفاجأت بالعثور على شارع تكسوه الأوراق وتحيط بها الأشجار.
But after the feeling of surprise, I felt shame.
ولكن بعد شعوري بالدهشة، شعرت بالعار.
How could I have been so blind?
كيف يمكن أن أكون أعمى هكذا؟
For an entire month,
لمدة شهر كامل،
I was so trapped in my mobile app
لقد كنت خاضعًا لتطبيق هاتفي
that a journey to work became one thing only:
الشيء الذي جعل الرحلة إلى العمل تصبح شيئًا واحدًا فقط:
the shortest path.
أقصر الطرق.
In this single journey, there was no thought
في هذه الرحلة الوحيدة، لم تكن هناك فكرة
of enjoying the road,
التمتع بـالطريق،
no pleasure in connecting with nature,
ولا المتعة في التواصل مع الطبيعة،
no possibility of looking people in the eyes.
ولا إمكانية للنظر في أعين الناس.
And why?
لماذا؟
Because I was saving a minute out of my commute.
لأنني كنت أوفر دقيقة في الرحلة.
Now let me ask you: Am I alone here?
الآن اسمحوا لي أن أسألكم: هل أنا وحيد هنا؟
How many of you have never used a mapping app for finding directions?
كم منكم لم يستخدم قط التطبيق الخاص بـالخرائط للعثور على الاتجاهات؟
Most of you, if not all, have.
معظمكم إن لم يكن كلكم، استخدمها.
And don't get me wrong -- mapping apps are the greatest game-changer
ولا تفهموني خطأ -تطبيقات رسم الخرائط هي أكبر مغير لقواعد اللعبة
for encouraging people to explore the city.
لتشجيع الناس على اكتشاف المدينة.
You take your phone out and you know immediately where to go.
تأخذ هاتفك الخاص وتعرف على الفور إلى أين تذهب.
However, the app also assumes
ومع ذلك، يفترض التطبيق أنه
there are only a handful of directions to the destination.
لا يوجد سوى عدد قليل من الاتجاهات نحو الوجهة.
It has the power to make those handful of directions
لديه القدرة على اقتراح ذلك العدد القليل من الاتجاهات
the definitive direction to that destination.
الاتجاه النهائي لتلك الوجهة.
After that experience, I changed.
بعد تلك التجربة، تغيرت.
I changed my research from traditional data-mining
لقد غيرت بحثي في قاعدة البيانات التقليدية
to understanding how people experience the city.
لفهم كيف يمكن للناس اكتشاف المدينة.
I used computer science tools
لقد استخدمت أدوات علم الحاسوب
to replicate social science experiments at scale, at web scale.
لتكرار تجارب العلوم الاجتماعية على مدى واسع على شبكة الإنترنت.
I became captivated by the beauty and genius
أصبحت أسير الجمال والعبقرية
of traditional social science experiments
لتجارب العلوم الاجتماعية التقليدية
done by Jane Jacobs, Stanley Milgram, Kevin Lynch.
التي قام بها كل من (جين جاكوبس) و(ستانلي ملغرام )و(كيفن لينش).
The result of that research has been the creation of new maps,
وكانت نتيجة تلك البحوث، إنشاء خرائط جديدة،
maps where you don't only find the shortest path, the blue one,
خرائط حيث يمكنك ايجاد أقصر الطرق، الطريق الازرق،
but also the most enjoyable path,
وأيضا الطريق الأكثر متعة،
the red one.
الطريق الاحمر.
How was that possible?
كيف كان ذلك ممكنًا؟
Einstein once said,
قال "اينشتاين" ذات مرة،
"Logic will get you from A to B.
"سوف يأخذك المنطق من (أ) إلى (ب).
Imagination will take you everywhere."
لكن، الخيال سيأخذك إلى أي مكان ".
So with a bit of imagination,
لذا بـقليل من الخيال،
we needed to understand
نحن بحاجة إلى فهم
which parts of the city people find beautiful.
أي جزء من المدينة يجده الناس جميلًا.
At the University of Cambridge, with colleagues,
في جامعة كامبريدج، مع الزملاء،
we thought about this simple experiment.
فكرنا في هذه التجربة البسيطة.
If I were to show you these two urban scenes,
إذا كشفت لكم عن مشهدين حضريين،
and I were to ask you which one is more beautiful,
وطلبت منكم أي واحد منهما هو الأكثر جمالًا،
which one would you say?
أي واحد ستقولون إنه الأجمل؟
Don't be shy.
لا تخجلوا.
Who says A? Who says B?
من قال (أ)؟ ومن قال (ب)؟
Brilliant.
رائع.
Based on that idea,
بناء على هذه الفكرة،
we built a crowdsourcing platform,
قمنا بإنشاء منصة التقييم الجماعي،
a web game.
لعبة على شبكة الإنترنت.
Players are shown pairs of urban scenes,
حيث يعرض على المشاركين زوج من المشاهد الحضرية،
and they're asked to choose which one is more beautiful, quiet and happy.
ويطلب منهم أن يختاروا أي واحد هو الأكثر جمالًا وهدوء وسعادة.
Based on thousands of user votes,
وبناء على الآلاف من أصوات المشاركين،
then we are able to see where consensus emerges.
نكون قادرين على رؤية ما يتفقون فيه.
We are able to see which are the urban scenes
وقادرين أيضًا على معرفة أي من المشاهد الحضرية
that make people happy.
التي تجعل الناس سعداء.
After that work, I joined Yahoo Labs,
بعد هذا العمل، انضممت إلى مختبرات ياهو،
and I teamed up with Luca and Rossano,
وتعاونت مع (لوكا وروسانو)،
and together, we aggregated those winning locations in London
ومعًا، استطعنا تجميع تلك المواقع الفائزة في لندن
to build a new map of the city,
لبناء خريطة جديدة للمدينة،
a cartography weighted for human emotions.
خرائط تراعي المشاعر الإنسانية.
On this cartography, you're not only able to see and connect
في هذه الخرائط، لا يمكنك فقط رؤية الطريق الأقصر
from point A to point B the shortest segments,
من النقطة (أ) إلى النقطة (ب)،
but you're also able to see the happy segment,
ولكن يمكنك أيضًا رؤية الطريق الأكثر سعادة،
the beautiful path, the quiet path.
والطريق الجميل والطريق الهادئ.
In tests, participants found the happy, the beautiful, the quiet path
في الاختبار، وجد المشاركون الطريق السعيد والجميل والهادئ
far more enjoyable than the shortest one,
أكثر متعة من الطريق الأقصر،
and that just by adding a few minutes to travel time.
وذلك فقط عن طريق إضافة بضع دقائق لمدة السفر.
Participants also love to attach memories to places.
أحب المشاركين أيضًا إرفاق ذكريات للأماكن.
Shared memories -- that's where the old BBC building was;
ذكريات مشتركةــ هناك كان المبنى القديم ل بي بي سي؛
and personal memories -- that's where I gave my first kiss.
وذكريات شخصية -هنا كانت أول قبلة.
They also recalled how some paths smelled and sounded.
وأشاروا أيضًا إلى رائحة وصوت بعض المسارات.
So what if we had a mapping tool
ولكن ماذا لو كان لدينا أداة رسم الخرائط
that would return the most enjoyable routes
التي من شأنها أن تدلنا على الطرق الأكثر متعة
based not only on aesthetics
ليس فقط على أساس الروعة
but also based on smell, sound, and memories?
ولكن أيضًا على أساس الرائحة، والصوت، والذكريات؟
That's where our research is going right now.
هذا ما تجري عليه أبحاثنا في الوقت الحالي.
More generally, my research,
وبشكل أعم، تقوم أبحاثنا
what it tries to do is avoid the danger of the single path,
على محاولة تجنب الخطر في بعض الطرق،
to avoid robbing people of fully experiencing the city in which they live.
لتجنب السرقة التي يعاني منها الناس بشكل كبير في المدينة التي يعيشون فيها.
Walk the path through the park, not through the car park,
أسلك الطريق من خلال الحديقة، وليس من خلال موقف السيارات،
and you have an entirely different path.
وسيكون لديك مسار مختلف تمامًا.
Walk the path full of people you love
أسلك المسار المليء بـالناس الذين تحبهم
and not full of cars,
وليس المليء بـالسيارات،
and you have an entirely different path.
وسيكون لديك مسار مختلف تمامًا.
It's that simple.
الأمر بهذه البساطة.
I would like to end with this thought:
أود أن اختم بـهذه الفكرة:
do you remember "The Truman Show?"
هل تذكرون "عرض ترومان؟"
It's a media satire in which a real person
إنها هجاء وسائل الإعلام حيث يجهل شخص حقيقي
doesn't know he's living in a fabricated world.
إنه يعيش في عالم مصطنع.
Perhaps we live in a world fabricated for efficiency.
ربما نعيش في عالم مصطنع للفعالية.
Look at some of your daily habits,
ألق نظرة على بعض عاداتك اليومية،
and as Truman did in the movie, escape the fabricated world.
وكما فعل "ترومان" في الفيلم، أهرب من العالم المصطنع.
Why?
لماذا؟
Well, if you think that adventure is dangerous, try routine. It's deadly.
حسنًا، إذا كنت تعتقد أن المغامرة خطرة، فجرب الرتابة. فإنها قاتلة.
Thank you.
شكرًا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)